Alfred P. Rockwell Papers 1846-1903 Mss.B.R59p
American Philosophical Society
Alfred P. Rockwell Papers
1846-1903
Mss.B.R59p
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet Ca. 8 volumes; 60 items
After receiving his PhB at Yale's Sheffield Scientific School in 1858, Alfred P. Rockwell continued his studies at the Museum of Practical Geology in London and the Bergakademie Freiberg, focused largely on mining engineering and coal geology. After service in the Civil War, he held positions at Yale and MIT before leaving academia in 1873 to pursue other opportunities. He later served as president of the Eastern Rail Road and Treasurer of the Great Falls Manufacturing Company, a textile firm in New Hampshire. The small collection of the papers of Alfred P. Rockwell document his interest in coal geology during the period of his postgraduate study at the Museum of Practical Geology and the Bergakademie, 1858-1859. Although the correspondence is slight, the collection includes a suite of notes on collieries, coal mining technology, and the economics of coal. Of particular note in the collection are the eight notebooks on mining engineering (some containing sketches), including two volumes of notes on John Percy's lectures at the Museum of Practical Geology, 1858, three volumes kept during his stay at the Bergakademie Freiberg, including one on a course on metallurgy taught by Bernhard von Cotta, 1858-1859, and one of an industrial tour through Germany and Belgium (June 1859). The other volumes include two on collieries in northern England, and one including of production records for the Great Falls Manufacturing Company, 1879-1886.
Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
Related Archival Materials note
The Institute Archives and Special Collections at MIT houses a small collection of the papers of Alfred P. Rockwell, 1868-1869, pertaining to his appointment at MIT. The Beinecke Library, Yale, includes a diary of Rockwell's kept during a visit to the Menominee Indians of Wisconsin, 1855-1856, as well as a set of lecture notes kept during a course on metallurgy, 1857.
The Godkin Family Papers (MS Am 1083.2) at the Houghton Library, Harvard, includes several letters written to Rockwell and his wife.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired 1983 and 1984 (accn. no 1983-1019ms, 1984-551ms).
Scope and Contents note
The small collection of the papers of Alfred P. Rockwell document his interest in coal geology during the period of his postgraduate study at the Museum of Practical Geology, London, and the Bergakademie Freiberg, 1858-1859. Although the correspondence is slight, the collection includes a suite of notes on collieries, coal mining technology, and the economics of coal.
Of particular note in the collection are the eight notebooks on mining engineering (some containing sketches), including two volumes of notes on John Percy's lectures at the Museum of Practical Geology, 1858, three volumes kept during his stay at the Bergakademie Freiberg, including one on a course on metallurgy taught by Bernhard von Cotta, 1858-1859, and one of an industrial tour through Germany and Belgium (June 1859). The other volumes include two on collieries in northern England, and one including of production records for the Great Falls Manufacturing Company, 1879-1886.
Biographical/Historical note
Born into a prominent Connecticut family, the geologist, educator, and industrialist Alfred Perkins Rockwell (1834-1903) was at turns a war hero, a professor, and a corporate executive. The son of a two-term Whig congressman, Rockwell received his AB from Yale in 1855, and remained in New Haven for his MA and PhB (1858) at the Sheffield Scientific School. Looking to build a foundation for a career in geology, he furthered his education by taking the standard European tour, spending time at the Museum of Practical Geology in London and at the prestigious Bergakademie at Freiberg, Saxony, where he studied metallurgy and coal geology. During his European sojourn, Rockwell also visited a succession of collieries in Northern England and Germany, familiarizing himself with advanced mining technology and with the economics of the industry.
At the outset of the Civil War, Rockwell returned to the United States and accepted a commission as Captain of the 1st Connecticut Light Artillery, earning a promotion to Colonel of the 6th Connecticut Infantry during the Petersburg Campaign of 1864 and finally a brevet to Brigadier General. He married Katharine Virginia Foote (1839-1902) after mustering out of the service in June 1865, and served briefly on the Board of Visitors at the U.S. Military Academy before returning to his alma mater as professor of mining at the Sheffield School. Barely three years later, he moved to a similar position at MIT, however by 1873, he made the decision to leave academia for other opportunities. In the aftermath of the devastating fire of 1872 that consumed much of downtown Boston, Rockwell was appointed Chairman of the Board of the Fire Commissioners in Boston, after which he served president of the Eastern Railroad (1876-1879) and from 1879 until his retirement in 1886, as treasurer of the Great Falls (N.H.) Manufacturing Co., a textile firm. Rockwell also earned income from land and other investments, including stock in the Minas Nuevas Mining Company, a lead and silver mining company in Mexico.
Never a prolific scholar, Rockwell wrote two books, Great Fires and Fire Extinction (Boston: Little, Brown, 1878) and Roads and Pavements in France (NY: Wiley, 1896). He and his wife had four children, of whom only one survived to adulthood: Mary Foote (1868-1868), Frances Beatrice (1872-1886), Samuel Edmund Foote (1873-1884), and Diana Ward (b. 1873). Rockwell died at his home in New Haven on Dec. 24, 1903.
Bergakademie Freiberg; Cotta, Berhnard von, 1808-1879; Great Falls Manufacturing Company; Massachusetts Institute of Technology.; Museum of Practical Geology (Great Britain); Percy, John, 1817-1889; Rockwell, Katherine Virginia Foote, 1839-1902; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School.; Coal mines and mining--Germany; Coal mines and mining--Great Britain; Geology--Germany; Geology--Great Britain; Metallurgy--Study and teaching; Mining engineering--Great Britain; Pencil works; Photographs; Railroads--Massachusetts; Textile industry--New Hampsire
- Series I. Correspondence and notes, 1846-1903; 3 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1867 Oct. 11; 4p.; Atkinson, W. G.
  - Backworth Colliery -- Accounts, 1856-1858; 14p.
  - Backworth Colliery -- Abstract of work done and cost of borehole, 1856-1858; 2p.
  - Circular coke ovens -- Cost estimate, 1858; 1p.
  - Coke ovens -- Sketch, construction, 1858 May 26; 1p.
  - Collieries -- Miscellany, 1858-1859; 8 items
  - Memorandum of agreement re: collieries, 1856 Mar. 29; 11p.; D'Arcy, George Frederick, Earl of Durham
  - Durham Colliery -- Pumping account, 1857 Aug.; 1p.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1866 Mar. 15; 2p.; Elliott, Charles W.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1871 June 11; 3p.; Elliott, F. B.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1881 Nov. 11; 3p.; Farnsworth, Fred
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1866-1867; 2 items; Gerolt, Baron von
  - Hetton Colliery -- Specification for the building of 50 Pitmen's cottages at Hetton, 1855 June 21; 4p.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1879 Dec. 10; 1p.; Hornby, John
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1878 Nov. 4; 2p.; Jackson, George E. B.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1879 Feb. 29; 2p.; Janin, Louis
  - Kilnhurst, Yorkshire -- Specification and contract for sinking a shaft at Kilnhurst, 1858; 4p.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1879 Apr. 9; 4p.; King, George B.
  - ALS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1879 Oct. 17; 1p.; Knight, Octavius
    Scope and Contents note
    Re: 50 shares of stock in the Norton House and Ship Ventilator Co.
  - Lund Hill Colliery -- List of prices paid to Colliers and other workmen, 1858; 1p.
  - Form for receiving coal in deeding away real estate, 1865 Mar.; 2p.; Mason, James
  - Minas Nuevas Mining Co., 1879 1881-1884; 3 items
  - Mining accounts (cost of making crib bed), n.d.; 4p.
  - Oaks Colliery -- Abstract of the Lease..., 1846 July 15; 4p.
  - Oaks Colliery, Yorkshire -- Ventilation returns, 1859; 1p.
  - Pouson's Treatise on coal mining (notes), n.d.; 2p.
  - Railroads -- Litigations of Eastern Rail Road, 1877; 8p.
  - Report on the system pursued in working coal in the West Riding of the County of York..., 1853 May; 8p.; Robson, George
  - Accounts, 1879-1881; 5p.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Biographical notes, 1903; 3p.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Financial correspondence, 1867-1888; 12 items; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Lectures on meteorology and Outline of Lectures on Astronomy, pp. 17-24; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
    Printed outlines with mss. notes by Rockwell.
  - ALsS to Joe, 1881-1883; 6 items; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Memorandum of enquiries in relation to coal and coal mines, 17p.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Norwich Grammar School report card, 1849 June 16; 1p.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Notes from Pal. Rep. on accidents in mines, 1835, ca.1858?; 7p.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Photograph of Alfred P. and daughter Diana W. Rockwell, 5p.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - ALsS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1866; 2 items; Rockwell, Charles H.
  - ALsS to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1864-1865; 2 items; Rockwell, John A.
  - Estate, 1861-1879; 4 items; Rockwell, John A.
  - Rockwell, Katharine, 1865-1888; 11 items
  - Rockwell-Elliott Family genealogy, n.d.; Cy, 6p.
  - West Auckland Colliery -- Construction accounts, 1858 May 26; 1p.
  - Wharncliffe Silkstone Colliery -- Account of strata in the neighbourhood, 1856 June; Cy, 2p.
- Series II. Notebooks, 1857-1886; 8 volumes
  - Lectures on Metallurgy by Dr. John Percy, FRS, 1857 Oct. 23; 1; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
    For lectures held at the Museum of Practical Geology, London.
  - Lectures on Metallurgy by Dr. John Percy, FRS, 1857 Nov.; 2; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Notes on Collieries near Barnsby, Yorkshire, 1858 July 30; 3; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
    Includes pencil sketches.
  - Notes on Collieries in Yorkshire and Scotland, 1858; 4; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Notes from Prof. Cotta's Gesteinlehre, Freiburg, 1858-1859; 5; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
    Includes rough pencil sketch of Niagara Falls, based on Bernhard von Cotta's lecture. In German and English.
  - "Freiburg", 1859; 6; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Tour in the Harz [and other notes on geology in Germany, Belgium), 1859 June 25; 7; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Great Falls Mfg. Co. Record of textile milling, 1879-1886; 8; 1 vol.; Rockwell, Alfred Perkins, 1834-1903
  - Freiburg, 1859; 9; 1 vol.
    Includes pencil sketches
    Custodial History note
    Transferred from the Connecticut Historical Society in May 2012, Accession number M2012-04